{"tossups": [{"question": "A pilot from this nation unwittingly earned a one-hundred thousand dollar prize from the U.S. Air Force when he turned over of a Soviet MiG-15 fighter. Hatchet-wielding soldiers from this nation killed American servicemen in the Joint Security Area, to which the U.S. responded by mobilizing an entire taskforce to cut down a poplar tree in Operation Paul Bunyan. The Demilitarized Zone is shared between a southern neighbor and, for ten points, what East Asian nation dominated for seven decades by the Kim family?", "answer": "<b><u>North Korea</u></b> (accept <b><u>Democratic People's Republic of Korea</u></b>; or <b><u>Chos\u014fn</u></b> <b><u>Minjuju\u016di Inmin Konghwaguk</u></b>; or <b><u>DPRK</u></b>; accept <b><u>DPR Korea</u></b>; accept <b><u>Bukhan</u></b>; prompt on partial answer)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man piloted a Gonzalo Coelho [[koo-EL-hoh]] voyage to Brazil which encountered its discoverer, Pedro Cabral. This Florentine worked for merchant Gianotto Berardi, who was an early investor in the 1492 Columbus expedition. The cartographer Martin Waldseem\u00fcller [[VAHLD-zee-MEW-luh]] was influenced by the Soderini letter to name a landmass for this explorer. For ten points, what Italian navigator, who is credited with coining the term \"New World, is the namesake of two continents in the western hemisphere?", "answer": "Amerigo <b><u>Vespucci</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The winning side of this battle issued Order Number 227 before its start, commanding soldiers to take \"not a step back.\" Mamayev [[MAH-mah-yev]] Kurgan and Pavlov\u2019s House were heavily contested locales during this battle. Romanian and German forces in this battle were encircled by Operation Uranus, led by Georgy Zhukov. For ten points, name this battle where Friedrich Paulus\u2019s Sixth Army failed to take a city on the Volga named for the leader of the Soviet Union.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Stalingrad</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Polish forces deployed an armored variant of this product known as the \"FT-B\" in an effort to repel a Russian invasion during the 1920 Polish-Soviet War. The creator of this product joked that you can have it \"any color, so long as it is black\" during a board meeting. This was the most sold automobile of the early 20th century. The \"Tin Lizzie\" was a nickname for, for ten points, which first mass-produced car created by the Ford Motor Company?", "answer": "Ford <b><u>Model T</u></b> (prompt on \"Tin Lizzie\" before mentioned; prompt on \"Ford\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Dirt brought from this state was used to bury the Marquis [[mahr-KEE]] de Lafayette in Paris. The storming of this state's Springfield Armory occurred during Shays' Rebellion, an uprising of disenchanted Revolutionary War veterans. Israel Putnam legendarily said \"Don't fire 'til you see the whites of their eyes\" at a 1775 engagement with the Redcoats in this state. The Battle of Bunker Hill occurred in, for ten points, what New England state?", "answer": "<b><u>Massachusetts</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This figure held 1960s jazz concerts in his backyard, including acts like Dave Brubeck and Dizzy Gillespie, to raise funds for the Southern Christian Leadership Conference. This founder of the Black-owned Freedom National Bank was defended by teammate Pee-Wee Reese by saying \"You can hate a man for many reasons. Color is not one of them.\" The first Black man to break the color barrier in Major League Baseball was, for ten points, which Brooklyn Dodgers baseball player?", "answer": "Jackie <b><u>Robinson</u></b> (or Jack Roosevelt <b><u>Robinson</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The outbreak of the Austro-Turkish war forced this composer to move from Vienna to Alsegrund. This man employed his own sister-in-law Josefa Weber [[yoh-SEH-fah VEH-buh]] to perform the role of Queen of the Night in one opera. The marriage of the Emperor's niece led to the city of Prague commissioning this composer's <em>Don Giovanni</em>. <em>The Marriage of</em> <em>Figaro</em> and <em>The Magic Flute</em> were written by, for ten points, which German-language composer of the 18th century?", "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus <b><u>Mozart</u></b> (accept Johannes Chrysostomus Wolfgangus Theophilus <b><u>Mozart</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Roy Choi created a popular variety of these objects in southern California known as Kogi. A variety of these objects that often frequent construction sites are known as \u201croach coaches.\u201d In accordance with its roots, a popular New England variety of these objects called Roxy\u2019s sells a product known as the Green Muenster. These objects may have grown out of the chuck wagon. In the 1970s, Raul Martinez pioneered the use of these objects to sell tacos. For ten points, name these vehicles where one can grab a meal.", "answer": "<b><u>Food Truck</u></b>s (prompt on \"truck(s)\")", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Frederick Jackson Turner's Frontier Thesis claims \"American Democracy\" was not established on this object or the <em>Susan Constant</em>. The springing of a leak by the accompanying <em>Speedwell</em> led to William Bradford deciding to solely use this ship for a western voyage. A rudimentary government for Plymouth known as its namesake \"Compact\" was signed on this vessel. For ten points, name this ship that transported the Pilgrims to the New World.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Mayflower</u></b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "William Hogarth depicted a young merchant wasting his money in this city and eventually being placed in its Fleet Prison in <em>A Rake's Progress</em>. Waterloo Bridge and Charing Cross Bridge are included in Claude Monet's scenes from this city, which include a series on the <em>Houses of Parliament</em>. Canaletto painted <em>The Thames and the City</em> depicting, for ten points, which English capital city that contains the Tate Modern?", "answer": "<b><u>London</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In this city's amphitheater, Pink Floyd member David Gilmour gave the first public concert here in over 1,900 years. This site includes the ancient House of the Surgeon, as well as several artworks depicting Greek mythology in the House of the Tragic Poet. The <em>Alexander Mosaic</em> is found in this site's House of the Faun, which occupies an entire <em>insula</em>. For ten points, name this city which, along with Herculaneum, was destroyed by the 79 C.E. eruption of Mount Vesuvius.", "answer": "<b><u>Pompeii</u></b> (or <b><u>Pumpeje</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "One leader of this nation launched the Infitah [[in-fee-TAH]] policy, which \"opened the door\" to western investment. During a parade celebrating Operation Badr [[BAD-er]] in this nation, that leader was assassinated by members of the Islamic Jihad. Protests in this country's Tahrir Square in 2011 led to the ousting of long-time president Hosni Mubarak. Since 2014, Abdel Fattah el-Sisi has served as president of, for ten points, what Arab nation governed from Cairo?", "answer": "<b><u>Egypt</u></b> (or <b><u>Misr</u></b>; accept Arab Republic of <b><u>Egypt</u></b>; or Jumh\u016br\u012byat <b><u>Mi\u1e63r</u></b> al-\u02bbArab\u012byah; or Gomhoreyyet <b><u>Ma\u1e63r</u></b> el-\u02bfArabeyya)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This ruler approached his cousin of the same name to force him to become dictator, though that Grand Duke responded by pointing a pistol at his own head and threatening to fire. That episode occurred during the Revolution of 1905, in which this ruler's forces fired on demonstrators during \"Bloody Sunday\" at the Winter Palace. The Russo-Japanese War was lost by, for ten points, which Tsar who was later killed by the Bolsheviks?", "answer": "<b><u>Nicholas II</u></b> (accept <b><u>Nikolai II</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Postmaster General in the Harding Cabinet, Will H. Hays, names a regulatory \"Code\" for this industry, which banned depictions of \"homosexuality\" and \"unnecessary violence.\" The revival of the Second Ku Klux Klan in Stone Mountain, Georgia was sparked by a production in this industry called <em>Birth of a Nation</em>. For ten points, name this industry whose studios were forbidden from owning theaters in the court case <em>United States v.</em> <em>Paramount Pictures</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Film</u></b> (accept the <b><u>Movie</u></b> Industry; accept <b><u>Motion Picture</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In one poem, William Wordsworth referred to this site as an \"Inmate of lonesome Nature's endless year.\" After stabbing Alec, Tess of the D'urbervilles finally surrenders to police at this monument, which lies in Wiltshire. The works of William Stukeley led to the popular connection between this monument and the order of druids. For ten points, name this prehistoric monument on the Salisbury Plain that is often featured in British literature.", "answer": "<b><u>Stonehenge</u> </b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man was unknowingly given small dosages of methamphetamines by Max Jacobson, who was nicknamed \"Dr. Feelgood.\" This politician defeated incumbent Henry Cabot Lodge Jr. in a 1952 Senate race. This president negotiated with Nikita Khrushchev [[KROO-shev]] during the Cuban Missile Crisis and was in office during the botched Bay of Pigs invasion. The youngest person ever elected president was, for ten points, which Massachusetts politician?", "answer": "<b><u>John</u></b> F. <b><u>Kennedy</u></b> (both underlined portions required; accept <b><u>JFK</u></b>; prompt on \"Kennedy\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A thinker from this country criticized the Gotha [[GOH-tah]] Programme of its Social Democratic Party in one pamphlet. Another thinker from this country argued that a \u201cProtestant work ethic\u201d enabled the development of modern capitalism and suggested that the state held a monopoly on the legitimate use of violence. Two writers originally from this country wrote the <em>Communist Manifesto</em>. For ten points, name this homeland of Friedrich Engels, Max Weber [[VEH-buh]], and Karl Marx.", "answer": "<b><u>Germany</u></b> (or <b><u>Deutschland</u></b>; accept <b><u>German</u></b> Reich; or <b><u>Deutsches</u></b> Reich; accept the Kingdom of <b><u>Prussia</u></b> or K\u00f6nigreich <b><u>Preu\u00dfen</u></b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Under this prime minister, a scandal over the merger of Westland Helicopters</u></b> <b><u>led to the resignation of Defense Secretary Michael Heseltine. \u201cFlying (+)</u> pickets\u201d were used by National Union of Mineworkers during a strike under this prime minister. This leader\u2019s victory in the Falklands War allowed a landslide Conservative victory in the 1983 (*) </b>general election. For ten points, name this \u201cIron Lady,\u201d the prime minister of the United Kingdom during the 1980s.", "answer": "Margaret <b><u>Thatcher</u></b> (or Margaret Hilda <b><u>Thatcher</u></b>; Baroness <b><u>Thatcher</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Antikythera [[AN-tih-kih-THEER-uh]] mechanism is believed to be the</u></b> <b><u>oldest example of an analogue type of this device. The Difference Engine was (+)</u> a prototype of one of these devices built by Charles Babbage. German engineer Konrad Zuse [[ZOO-suh]] developed the Z3, the first programmable digital example of these devices, during World War (*) </b>Two. For ten points, name these devices that rapidly carry out mathematical operations, the \"science\" for which was pioneered by Alan Turing.", "answer": "<b><u>Computer</u></b>s (accept Analogue <b><u>Computer</u></b>s; or Electromechanical <b><u>Computer</u></b>; or <b><u>Computer</u></b> Science; prompt on \"calculator\" or \"mechanical calculator\")", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {"question": "<b><u>This party accepted opponent William Pitt Kellogg's election as governor of</u></b> <b><u>Louisiana in exchange for house seats in the Wheeler Compromise. This party's</u></b> <b><u>historical factions included the white supremacist (+)</u> Redeemers, the pro-big business Bourbons, and the Populists of William Jennings Bryan. This party controlled the \"Solid South,\" though it lost control of Southern states during the Reagan era. Represented by a (*) </b>donkey, for ten points, what U.S. political party opposes the Republicans?", "answer": "<b><u>Democrat</u></b>ic Party (or <b><u>Democrat</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This person's first purported miracle occurred when a locket containing their</u></b> <b><u>image supposedly rid Monica Besra of a malignant tumor. This figure faced</u></b> <b><u>controversy for her tacit support of her homeland's Hoxha [[HOH-shuh]] regime (+)</u></b> <b>and Indira Gandhi's suspension of civil liberties during \"The Emergency.\" This woman of Albanian descent founded the Missionaries of Charity and served the slums of (*) </b>Kolkata. For ten points, name this Nobel Peace Prize winner and canonized nun of the 20th century.", "answer": "Mother <b><u>Teresa</u></b> (accept Mary <b><u>Teresa</u></b> Bojaxhiu; accept Saint <b><u>Teresa</u></b> of Calcutta)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This monument\u2019s astylar design was developed by the Neoclassical sculptor</u></b> <b><u>Jean Chalgrin [[SHAHL-grin]]. The base of this monument contains four sculptural</u></b> <b><u>groups, including one by Antoine (*)</u> Etex said to commemorate the Peace of 1815 and one by Fran\u00e7ois [[frahn-SWAH]] Rude called </b><em><b>Departure of the Volunteers of 1792</b></em><b>. The Tomb of the Unknown Soldier beneath this monument was commissioned after the Battle of (*) </b>Austerlitz. For ten points, name this monument found at the western end of the Champs-\u00c9lys\u00e9es [[SHAHMPS eh-lee-SAY]] in Paris.", "answer": "<b><u>Arc de Triomphe</u></b> de l'\u00c9toile (accept <b><u>Triumphal Arch of the Star</u></b>; prompt on partial answers in English)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man urged the common British person to abandon so-called \"dying</u></b> <b><u>metaphors\" in his essay \"Politics and the English Language.\" This writer's</u></b> <b><u>participation in the POUM (*)</u> party's militia during the Spanish Civil War inspired his autobiographical </b><em><b>Homage to Catalonia</b></em><b>. This man's time as police sub-commandant in British Burma inspired his short story \"Shooting an Elephant.\" The rise of totalitarianism (*) </b>inspired, for ten points, which British writer's <em>1984</em> and <em>Animal Farm</em>?", "answer": "George <b><u>Orwell</u></b> (accept Eric Arthur <b><u>Blair</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Dominique de Gourgues [[GOORZH]] temporarily reestablished French</u></b> <b><u>hegemony in the north of this state by seizing Fort Caroline. A 1521 voyage to this</u></b> <b><u>modern state ended with its leader dying following a skirmish with the Calusa people.</u></b> <b><u>(*)</u> The oldest continuously inhabited settlement in the U.S. is in this state. The </b><em><b>conquistador</b></em><b> Juan Ponce de Leon searched for the \"Fountain of (*) </b>Youth\" in, for ten points, which Southern U.S. state that contains St. Augustine?", "answer": "<b><u>Florida</u></b> (accept La <b><u>Florida</u></b>; or <b><u>Floride</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Gepid king Ardaric quickly collapsed an empire named for these people after</u></b> <b><u>gathering its former subject tribes and defeating them at the Battle of Nedao [[NEH-</u><u>dow]]. Allied with the Visigothic king Theoderic, (+)</u> the Roman general Flavius Aetius [[AY-shus]] stopped these people's advance into Western Europe at the Battle of the Catalaunian Plains. Much of 5th century (*) </b>Europe was ravaged by, for ten points, what nomadic people led by Attila?", "answer": "<b><u>Hun</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Hun</u></b>nic people; or <b><u>Hun</u></b>nish)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This leader was born in the Duchy of Bar and petitioned Robert de</u></b> <b><u>Baudricourt [[bahw-dreh-KOR]] for an escort to Paris. This figure, who was sent by</u></b> <b><u>Charles VII [[the seventh]] to (+)</u> relieve a besieged city following a vision from Saint Catherine of Alexandria, was captured in 1430 by the Burgundian faction and burned at the stake by the (*) </b>English. For ten points, name this \"Maid of Orl\u00e9ans,\" [[ohr-LEH-ahn]] a French hero of the Hundred Years' War.", "answer": "Saint <b><u>Joan</u></b> of Arc (or <b><u>Jeanne</u></b> d'Arc; prompt on \"Maid of Orl\u00e9ans\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}